<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Stow, in the county of Bucks, on the ninth of September, 1683 being the day of thanksgiving appointed by the King's declaration, for acknowledging God's great mercy in discovering and defeating the late treasonable conspiracy against His Sacred Majesty's person and government / by Tho. Wagstaffe ...</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12369123</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12369123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60506</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65994)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 903:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Stow, in the county of Bucks, on the ninth of September, 1683 being the day of thanksgiving appointed by the King's declaration, for acknowledging God's great mercy in discovering and defeating the late treasonable conspiracy against His Sacred Majesty's person and government / by Tho. Wagstaffe ...</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Roycroft, for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs I, 10-16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60506:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60506:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at STOW, IN THE COUNTY of BUCKS, On the Ninth of <hi>September,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <p>BEING The Day of Thankſgiving Appointed by the KING's DECLARATION, FOR Acknowledging God's great Mercy in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering and Defeating the late Treaſonable Conſpiracy againſt His Sacred <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Perſon and Government.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO: WAGSTAFFE,</hi> M.A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Roycroft,</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 168<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:60506:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60506:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. I. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>10. <hi>My Son, if Sinners entice thee, conſent thou not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>11. <hi>If they ſay, Come with us, let us lay wait for Blood, let us lurk privily for the Innocent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>12. <hi>Let us ſwallow them up alive, as the Grave, and whole, as thoſe that go down into the Pit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. <hi>We ſhall find all precious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our houſes with ſpoil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>14. <hi>Caſt in thy lot among us, let us all have one purſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>15. <hi>My Son, walk not thou in the way with them, refrain thy foot from their path.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>16. <hi>For their feet run to evil, and make haſte to ſhed blood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THat <hi>Solomon</hi> (by theſe words) did not chiefly intend to caution men againſt joyning with common Thieves and Robbers, againſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king part with ſuch who made Stealing their Trade, and lay by the High-way to kill men for their Mony; but that he had a further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Thieves and Murderers of a more public nature; To ſuch Combinations and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60506:3"/>Confederacies as would pillage a Nation, and involve a Kingdom in Blood, ſeems not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable for theſe following Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is a ſet and continued diſcourſe, a thing carneſtly preſs'd and recommended for ſeveral Verſes together, which is unuſual in this Book, and perhaps there is not the like inſtance in the whole <hi>Proverbs;</hi> which ſhews, that the Matter here ſpoken of, is both of extraordinary weight, and alſo that there is ſome aptneſs and diſpoſition in men towards it, to be enſnar'd by it. Now though 'tis well to perſwade men from being common Rogues and Cut-throats, yet ſure there needs not much Cogency of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The matter is plain and obvious, and the leaſt Proverbial Sentence ſeems to be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warning. Open and barefac'd miſchief needs not great Wiſdom to diſcover, nor much diſcourſe or vehemency to forewarn. But there are Villanies that have Cloaks and Covers, fair and ſpecious ſhews, which require Art to unrip and take off; And there are creeping and contagious Evils, which eaſily infect the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and unwary; the unſtable and haſty are apt to ſwallow any Bait that is well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd. In theſe caſes therefore Caution is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and ſure 'tis not a fruitleſs earneſtneſs to adviſe men to beware of joyning with thoſe who may pretend they are plotting for God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60506:3"/>and conſpiring for Religion, when (in Truth) they are only <hi>lurking for blood, and laying wait for ſpoil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is Caution againſt Enticements, <hi>If Sinners entice thee.</hi> And do common Thieves do this? do they go about to gain a Party, and make themſelves ſtrong by Numbers? this is the way to ruine themſelves, and to lay them open to diſcovery; a few are ſufficient for the purpoſes of ſtealing, and if they meet with Men of the ſame complexion, they eaſily unite, and there needs no great ſubtilty and contrivance to make them agree in the ſame common work; but Aſſociations are for the mighty Deſtroyers. The Government is not eaſily oppos'd, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions and Inſurrections, (how few ſoever the Contrivers are) muſt be the work of a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. Men of this Character therefore are the <hi>Sinners</hi> that entice; They muſt have men to carry on their deſigns, and they have Agents and Emiſſaries in all parts of a Kingdom, to work upon the giddy, to ſeduce the unſettled or diſcontented. The great <hi>Enticers</hi> are the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Politic, that are skill'd in all the arts of Inſinuation; that are excellent at creating Fears and Jealouſies, whetting Diſcontents, and raiſing Storms in the minds of men; that can conjure up Dangers in the moſt merciful and orderly Government, and make men believe they are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60506:4"/>loſt and undone, when they are in the happieſt condition of any people in the World. Theſe then are <hi>Enticers</hi> to purpoſe, that can entice men out of their wits, that can make them believe Impoſſibilities and Contradictions, and give up their Faith to things, as irrational and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable as any Fable or Romance. And to this may be added, That to joyn together in common Stealing, needs not, nor can have any ſuch cunning Methods. What Arguments can there be to make a man a Thief? What fair flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes and pretences to win a man that hath any thing of Sobriety to their Company? When they go to rob, they do not tell one another, that they riſe to ſecure their Property, they fight for <hi>Liberty,</hi> and aſſociate in defence of Religion; but the buſineſs is plain and downright Villany. But Treaſon and Sedition may be ſmooth'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and there is art and contrivance to make men ſwallow <hi>Rebellion.</hi> The People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might be told they were a Free People, that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> invaded their Liberties and Priviledges, that therefore they did but themſelves juſtice if they took the cauſe into their own hands and righted themſelves; that their King was a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of Idolatry; that they were Gods People, and therefore ought to ſecure God's Rights as well as their own, and not ſuffer any Innovation to be made in Religion; that their taking up
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60506:4"/>Arms therefore would not be Rebellion, but a Spiritual work, a ſetting up God's Cauſe, and deſtroying his Enemies; That God gave the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> only to thoſe that worſhip'd him rightly and kept his Covenant, and that they were only the Perſons; that their King, and thoſe that adher'd to him had fall'n off from God, and therefore had forfeited all their propriety in the Government and the Land; That all the Right was devolv'd upon them the true Worſhippers, and they were (by Gods Donation) Heirs to the wicked and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous. And therefore in riſing againſt them, they did but take the beſt courſe they could to gain their own. Theſe or ſuch like ways of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticement might be us'd by deſigning Men; and ſuch a cauſe will allow of a great many ſlights and politic Pretences, whereas downright Thie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very will admit of none. Men cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded when they go to ſteal and kill, that they fight the Lords Battels, and deſtroy the wicked and Heathen in the Land. But Zeal and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſanctified Pretences may be ſet up to draw men into Rebellion and Treaſonable Conſpiracies; and therefore 'tis more likely that ſuch were the Sinners that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, that entic'd men to confederate with them. The conjunction of Thieves is but a Knot of a few; but this is an Aſſociation, a League, a Conſpiracy of many Murderers.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60506:5"/>3. Theſe Expreſſions ſeem to intimate the ſame thing; <hi>Let us ſwallow them up alive as the Grave, and whole as them that go down into the Pit: We ſhall find all precious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our Houſes with ſpoil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe import greater miſchief and cruelty, and greater gain than is uſually agreeable to the State of Confederate Robbers; for though they may now and then murder men by the High-way, though they may kill men in their beds, yet what is this to ſwallowing men up as the Grave, which ſwallows up Kingdoms, and devours whole Generations? 'Tis Inſurrections and Maſſacres that thus triumph in Blood. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Murderer kills a man, but 'tis only rebellious Leagues, and treaſonable Aſſociations that have a ſtomach like the Grave, that always eat and devour, but are never glutted nor ſatisfied. Neither is it for half a dozen Villains to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to themſelves and their Aſſociates ſuch mighty ſucceſs, as to ſwallow up all before them. But deep Confederacies that are numerous and ſtrong, that have made a great part of the People; Theſe may think to ſweep a Kingdom, may make their Multitudes an Argument to invite others, may encourage themſelves and their Party with the facility of their Enterprize, that they are able to ſwallow men that are alive, as the Grave does dead men; They ſhall eaſily ſeize
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60506:5"/>them, ſurprize them unawares, and the quick ſhall fall into their hands, as the Dead go into the Pit without ſtrugling, reſiſtance or oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>And then for that other branch, <hi>We ſhall find all precious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our Houſes with ſpoil.</hi> Theſe are not the returns of common Robberies: Men by taking a Purſe, or breaking open Houſes, do not expect to lay a foundation of wealth or greatneſs, by ſuch means to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves, and gain great Eſtates. But 'tis very profitable to fiſh in troubled Waters. The Common-wealth is a great Stake, and if it might be ſhar'd, would be a handſom ſupply for Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and Ambition. The Temple of <hi>Solomon</hi> (lately built) which being very coſtly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore perhaps Idolatrous, the Spoils of it would be a competent morſel, and to be ſure to kill the Heir and take his Inheritance. To ſeize the Revenues of the Crown and Church, is a way Ambitious and Deſigning men may have <hi>to find precious ſubſtance, and to fill their Houſes with ſpoil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Thoſe words immediately after the Text ſeem likewiſe to favour this Opinion, <hi>Surely in vain the Net is ſpread in the ſight of any Bird; And they lay wait for their own blood, they lurk privily for their own lives:</hi> that is, Thoſe bloody Attempts and Contrivances were in vain, they would not come to the iſſue the Plotters expected; for how
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60506:6"/>cloſe and privy ſoever they were manag'd and carry'd on. He (King <hi>Solomon</hi>) had knowledge of them, and in vain was the Net ſpread for him in his ſight; He knew their Devices and ſecret Machinations. So that at length the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief they intended would fall on their own heads, their laying in wait would catch their own Bloods, and their lurking privily would turn to a Conſpiracy againſt their own lives; for (upon Diſcovery) the Law would lay hold of them, and they would be brought to exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Reaſons, upon the account of which, I conceive, theſe Words of the Wiſe King had a main reſpect to Public Miſchiefs, to the Plots and Deſigns of wicked Men againſt him and his Government. And (if I may have leave to Conjecture) they may have a more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate relation to the Rebellious Principles and Practices, firſt ſet on foot in the time of <hi>David</hi> his Father; for tho, after the defeat and death of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> the King return'd and govern'd the Kingdom in Peace, yet it is not probable that all the Seeds of <hi>Sedition</hi> were ſo ſoon extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed. A Rebellious Ferment once raiſed in a People, tho it may be calm'd and quieted, yet it is apt to ſtir again upon any occaſion or opportunity. The ſame Principles, and many of the Perſons were ſtill in being, and tho for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60506:6"/>ſome time dormant, might again be quickned by Politic and diſcontented Perſons, and they might again be blown up to the ſame Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by the ſame plauſible Pretences that <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> had uſed before. Theſe things <hi>Solomon</hi> ſeems to have an eye to, and is vigilant againſt, and therefore earneſtly preſſes his People not to give ear to any ſuch Inſinuations. And (this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo) the Text is a Caveat not to be entic'd nor enſnar'd by them, <hi>My Son, if Sinners entice thee, conſent thou not. My Son,</hi> is a Compellation of love and kindneſs, and denotes the Fatherly Affection he had for his People. The King here then (if this Interpretation hits the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) exhorts all his loving Subjects not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain any mutinous and ſeditious Principles; to beware of thoſe Men that would tempt them into Leagues and Covenants of Blood and Rebellion. And to enforce this upon them, he tells them that the End of their Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies was only <hi>Murder</hi> and <hi>Spoil;</hi> and how fair ſoever they might ſeem, what allegations ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of Right and Juſtice they might make, they were but crafty Devices to intrap the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautelous, for in truth, <hi>Their feet run to evil, and make haſt to ſhed blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In diſcourſing of theſe Words I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To repreſent them in a manner ſuited to our own Circumſtances.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60506:7"/>2. To lay down the Iniquity of theſe Practices.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To enforce the Caution, That therefore we ought not to conſent, if we are entic'd to things of that Nature.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To lay down ſome Rules, as preventive Expedients to preſerve us from them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To repreſent theſe Words in a manner ſuited to our own Circumſtances.
<note place="margin">Apol. pag. 74. <hi>Nos eſſe homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes turbulentos, Regibus Sceptra de manibus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripere, populum armare, Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia evertere, Leges reſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, poſſeſſiones diſſipare, regna ad popularem ſtatum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care.</hi>
               </note> The Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> in his Apology for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when it had been objected by the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> That the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> wer turbulent Men, that they took away Scepters from Kings, that they arm'd the People, that they overturn'd Tribunals, that they laid aſide the Laws, that they broke in pieces mens Rights and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they turn'd Kingdoms to popular States, &amp;c. After a ſufficient deteſtation of all theſe things, and having ſaid, That the obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them againſt the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> was ſuch a Calumny as was caſt upon Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Anſwers thus,
<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 77. <hi>Arg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s enim Deo noſtro, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus haec ſolius cauſa eſt, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus regnes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſp. quae ad Evangel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um acceſſerunt, nullum unquam adhuc hujuſmodi exemplum extitiſſe. Nullum enim nos regnum evertimus, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us dition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m aut jura minuimus, Rempub. nullam turbavimus. Manent adhuc ſuo loco, &amp; avitâ dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Reges</hi> Angliae, Daniae, Suetiae, <hi>Duces</hi> Saxoniae, <hi>Comites</hi> Palatini, &amp;c. <hi>omnes eodem jure, eodemque ſtatu quo faerant antea vel potius, quia propter Evangelium populum habent obſequentiorem multo meliore. Eant ſane in illa loca, ubi nunc Dei beneficio auditur Evangelium, ubi plus majeſtatis? ubi minus faſtus &amp; Tyrannidis? ubi Princeps magis colitur? ubi Populus minus Tumultuatur? ubi unquam fuit pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica Res; ubi Eccleſia Tranquilltor?</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We give thanks to our God, whoſe Cauſe this is, that in all the Kingdoms, Dominions, Common-wealths, which have been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Goſpel, there is not ſo much as one Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60506:7"/>of any ſuch thing; for we have overturn'd no Kingdom, We have diminiſh'd no mans Dominion or Rights, We have diſturb'd no Common-wealths: Hitherto they remain in their own Condition, and in their Ancient Dignity; The Kings of</hi> England, Denmark, Sweedland, <hi>the Dukes of</hi> Saxony, <hi>the Counts</hi> Palatine, <hi>and other Proteſtant Principalities and Free Cities he there names. All theſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>have the ſame Rights, and are in the ſame ſtate they were before, or rather in a much better; becauſe by reaſon of the Goſpel they have their People much more Obedient. Let them go into thoſe Places where now, through Gods Bleſſing, the Goſpel is taught; Where is more Majeſty? Where leſs Pride and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny? Where is the Prince more Reverenc'd? Where are the People leſs Tumultuous? Where ever was the Common-wealth; where ever was the Church more quiet and peaceable?</hi> Thus far Biſhop <hi>Jewel.</hi> It is the Glory of the Reformation, that as it proceeded by the moſt peaceable and orderly Steps, ſo it held the moſt peaceable and orderly Doctrines. The firſt Reformers, neither in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion nor Practice, maintain'd any thing that was infeſtuous to Common-wealths, or injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Governours; and they juſtly pleaded, as the Primitive Chriſtians did, That they always paid Subjection to the Powers ſet over them; that their Behaviour was meek and gentle; that they always comply'd with the Will of their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60506:8"/>Rulers, where they lawfully might, and where they might not they ſubmitted with patience, and always choſe rather to ſuffer, than to be turbulent, ſeditious and unquiet: This was the firſt Reformation, and this is the true Proteſtant Doctrine. But alas! ſince that Time there hath riſen up another Proteſtant Religion, and another Reformation; there have been a Generation of Men of violent and furious Principles, who were for Reforming by Deſtruction, whoſe Religion was all Zeal, <hi>(i.e.) Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> and who inſtead of Obeying, were for Fighting and Rebelling for Conſcience ſake. We may remember when <hi>Conſcience</hi> took the Field, and marcht with Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Bullet, and brought a Proteſtant KING to the Block. And the Deliverance we this Day thank God for, manifeſts that theſe Principles are ſo far from being loſt, that they are height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and improv'd. This is a degree above Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and the meaſures of <hi>King-killing</hi> are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd very high when Blunderbuſſes are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to take off the Royal Family, and numbers of Confederates to follow the Blow. This Day therefore is the Text fulfill'd in our Ears, that there have been <hi>Sinners</hi> who have <hi>entic'd,</hi> who have ſaid, <hi>Come with us, caſt in thy lot among us,</hi> (i.e.) in plain Engliſh, <hi>Let us joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in an Aſſociation, let us Covenant one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let us lurk privily for the Innocent without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60506:8"/>cauſe.</hi> For the Innocent without Cauſe indeed! for what Cauſe had the King, and His Loyal Subjects given them, that they ſhould purſue His Life, and thirſt for their Blood? what mighty wrong had been done, that nothing but the ſudden deſtruction of Him and His Royal Brother, could expiate and ſatisfie? This is not, this cannot be alledged. Our Soveraign (God be thanked) is a Prince of incomparable Mercy and Goodneſs; All the Nation feels His Influence and His healing Hand; His Enemies not only live by His Favour, but thrive alſo by His Grace and Bounty: Some of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates themſelves have by Him been advanced to great Honours and Fortunes. And are theſe the Qualities that muſt be hunted to Death? Are theſe the Wrongs for which his People muſt be ſtirr'd up to worry Him? Should a Heathen hear that the KING was to be Piſtol'd, His Nobles murder'd, and His Kingdom rifled, he could not but conjecture, that he was a <hi>Nero</hi> at leaſt, a Prince fierce and cruel; that he delighted in Oppreſſion and Rapine; that he kill'd his Subjects for Sport and Triumph, and had done ſome unheard of Cruelties. But when Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is the moſt conſpicuous part of His Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; when His Mercy is thus far like God's, as to be <hi>over all his Work;,</hi> when He is in truth, the Breath of our Noſtrils, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60506:9"/>of our Eyes; what could exaſperate and provoke, even the worſt Natures to ſuch direful methods of Execution? Nothing but the moſt fell and ſalvage Diſpoſitions, ſuch as have the names of Men, but the Tempers of Wolves and Tigers, could engage Men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to <hi>ſwallow Him up alive as the Grave, and whole as thoſe that go down into the Pit.</hi> This is the firſt repreſenting theſe Words accommodate to the occaſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next is to lay down the Iniquity of theſe Practices; and this ſure needs no proof, it hath no ſubterfuge, evaſion, or excuſe. The Rebellious Spirits heretofore pretended the Face of Authority and a Parliamentary Power; but what is this to Plots and Inſurrections? they pretended to raiſe Men by the Kings Power, tho againſt His Perſon; and will His Politic Capacity extend likewiſe to authorize ſecret Devices and Treachery? They call'd their Forces the <hi>King's Armies,</hi> tho they fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Him; and are theſe the King's Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and the Kings Aſſociations too, which were intended to murder Him, and overturn His Government? They then call'd the People out to fight the <hi>Lords Battels;</hi> but ſurely they will not call theſe the <hi>Lord's Plots,</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Conſpiracies.</hi> Theſe things are too ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, and the moſt Cunning and Politic can
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60506:9"/>never clap ſuch a Face and Diſguiſe on them, as ſhall make them appear otherwiſe than hideous and monſtrous. Our Saviour practis'd his own Religion the moſt exactly, and then his Apoſtles, and next after them the Primitive Chriſtians; all theſe ſuffer'd under the Iniquity of their Governours: And what do they all but practiſe and preach Patience, Meekneſs, Gentleneſs, Submiſſion and Obedience? They do not revile nor reſiſt Authority; they do not aſſociate together to pull down the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, much leſs lay Plots to entrap the Lives of their Governours. <hi>Suffering</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> was Goſpel then, and <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was Sin in thoſe days. But ſure we need not go to Religion to diſprove this, Common Honeſty will lay open its Vileneſs; ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices are without, not only the Example of any good Chriſtian, but of any indifferently honeſt Heathen. Ev'n <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> deteſt ſuch things: All Governments and all Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths have abhorr'd Plots and Treacheries; and thoſe engaged in them have, by all ſorts of Men, been eſteem'd the Peſts of Government, and the Bane of all Society. To conſpire the death of any Man hath been always horrid and infamous; but to lurk privily for the Blood of Kings, and turn a Kingdom into ſlaughter, is a Miſchief of that magnitude, that we want
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60506:10"/>words to expreſs it. For as there are things of a tranſcendent Excellency which are too high to be pourtraited by Speech, and are better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd and conceiv'd than diſcourſed of; ſo there are likewiſe things of a contrary tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, Abominations not capable of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which are wicked even beyond words, and ſurpaſs deſcription, by reaſon of their Vileneſs. If therefore you would conceive, for I cannot expreſs, the Iniquity of thoſe Practices, Put your Thoughts into the moſt black and gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my poſture, conceive an Action that a Jeſuit would ſtartle at, muſter up the bloody Villanies that Hiſtories afford us; remember <hi>Ravilliac</hi> that ſtob'd <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> reflect on the Holy League, when ſo many thouſand Proteſtants were butcher'd: Conſider the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Treaſon,</hi> which was to blow up the King and the Parliament; caſt into your minds the Groans and Cries of the maſſacred by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and to theſe add the lamentable Miſeries of our own Civil Wars. All theſe ſad and ghaſtly things put together, may give us ſome Character of the buſineſs before us; for all theſe perhaps were allotted for our Doom: And who can tell the Miſeries of a Kingdom without a Head, and Fury and Slaughter ranging in every corner of it? Who can expreſs the diſmal Conſequences, when a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60506:10"/>Good KING ſhall be taken off by ſalvage Villains, and His Loyal People left at the mercy of Cruel and Blood-thirſty Men?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Enforce the Caution, That therefore we are not to conſent, if Sinners entice us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate in ſuch Practices, <hi>For their feet run to evil, and make haſte to ſhed blood.</hi> And this ſure is Argument enough to hinder Men from being taken by ſuch Enticements, for let the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals be never ſo large, the Means to accompliſh it never ſo feazable, yet if they are to end in Blood, 'tis an amazing Diſcouragement; tho <hi>precious ſubſtance</hi> is to be found, and our Houſes thereby to be <hi>fill'd with ſpoil,</hi> yet if they are to be got by Murder, it will ſtop any Man of but indifferent Principles from the Undertaking. And ſurely Aſſaſſinating a KING, and killing His Nobles and Magiſtrates, and turning a Kingdom into Blood, is Murder with a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. What Arguments the Principal Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates might uſe to entice others, and what horrid Salvo's they might pick up for their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, muſt be uncertain in ſuch dark and ſecret Conſpiracies: But it is certain that none of thoſe Maxims of Rebellion, which in the late Times were ſpread abroad to ſeduce the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, could have any colour of Pretence here; 'Twas then pretended, that the King levied War againſt his Parliament; that they fought not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60506:11"/>againſt Him, but his evil and malignant Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, and deſign'd no more but to bring Him to his Parliament, the great Council of the Nation, and the King's beſt Councellor: That the King, tho he was <hi>Singulis Major,</hi> yet he was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis Minor;</hi> tho he was greater than any Subject, yet he was leſs than all the People; that therefore the Repreſentative Body of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (legally choſen) might call him to account for Mal-adminiſtration of Government: That the Power of the Kingdom was in that Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective Body, and they might give out Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, and raiſe Arms and Men for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Theſe and ſuch like Maxims (firſt taken out of the Schools of the Jeſuits) were the Snares whereby unthinking Men were betray'd into Rebellion. But what can be pleaded in this Caſe? <hi>Blunderbuſſes</hi> and <hi>Piſtols</hi> are a ſure way indeed to take a King from evil Councellors; but when they are levell'd at his Coach, it can hardly be ſaid that they are not deſign'd againſt Him, but a malignant Party about him. Wicked People may combine together and endeavour an Inſurrection; but ſure they can't call Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Lawful Authority;</hi> they can't ſay, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federating Miſcreants are greater than the <hi>King,</hi> the Peoples Repreſentative, and have the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power of the Kingdom. The truth is, here the Vizard is taken off and <hi>Treaſon</hi> appears
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60506:11"/>bare-fac'd, and in its own Colours: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other Face or pretended Countenance, the thing is downright Killing the KING, and raiſing an Inſurrection in His Kingdoms. The Caution therefore (in this Caſe) is very force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; for if the moſt plauſible Pretences for Rebellion have not Plea enough to tempt any honeſt Man, what Enticements muſt thoſe be which have none? The Concluſion therefore is very firm from theſe Premiſſes, <hi>If Sinners entice thee</hi> to ſuch Practices, <hi>conſent thou not:</hi> If theſe things be ſo very Evil, ſo very Bloody, then the adviſing not to joyn in them is an act, as of Conſcience towards God, ſo of Kindneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men. He that ſees a dangerous Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice, which others are blindly falling into, and calls to them to beware, deſerves as well thanks for his love, as praiſe for his fore-ſight. It is therefore the Goodneſs, as well as Wiſdom of Diſcerning Princes, when they find ſubtle and deſigning Men buſie in perverting and drawing away their People; to forewarn them of the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, to lay open their Baits, to uncover their ſecret and lurking Deſigns, that thoſe who have not abilities to conſider the depth and myſtery of ſuch Arts, ſhould not unwarily be taken and enſnar'd by them to their own damage. This ſeems to be the meaning of the words of the Text, the Caution King <hi>Solomon</hi> gives to his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60506:12"/>People againſt confederating with <hi>Men of Blood.</hi> And this is one end of His Majeſties <hi>Declaration,</hi> diſcovering the Devices of Crafty and Wicked Men, that ſo His Subjects might not be tempted by any Pretences that Cunning and Deſigning Men might make to draw them in; which evidences as well his Affections to his People, as Care to preſerve his own Perſon and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And it is an Inſtance of his Fatherly Care to forewarn his People from ſwallowing down any Enticements of that Nature, from entring into ſuch Company, whoſe Converſe and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour is of ſo dark and bloody a Character; And it is our duty, not only in Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, not only in Allegiance and ſtrict Duty and Juſtice; but in gratitude likewiſe to our King, to be extremely cautious of all ſuch Inſinuations, of all Devices that would draw us into Blood, Sedition, or Rebellion. Which that we may the better do, we may conſider,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Some Rules and Directions, as Expedients preventive of ſuch Confederacies and ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Be not over-bold and ready to Cenſure the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> This is a Duty we owe to one another, much more to the Government; and as enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the faireſt Thoughts of Men, and of their Actions, contributes exceedingly to the quiet of Neighbourhood, ſo uſing the ſame
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60506:12"/>towards our Governours, would be an excellent Expedient for Civil Peace: And certainly the height of their Station, and difficulty of their Work, the multiplicity of the Affairs of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours ſhould challenge from us a candid and favourable Conſtruction of their Actions. When the Wiſeſt do often miſcarry in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of little Matters, when we often commit Diſorders and Errors in the Government of our Private Families; do we think that the Rule of a Kingdom, and the great Buſineſs of a Nation, can be always manag'd like the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, without the leaſt Miſtake or Fault? 'Tis therefore monſtrous and impious Diſingenuity, to load every Miſcarriage of State, with Reproach, Bitterneſs, and foul Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: And 'tis much worſe yet, to call thoſe Miſtakes, which are the beſt Rules. The Art of Governing is an abſtruſe thing, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences and Effects of it are like the Hand of a Watch, viſible to all; but the way whereby theſe are mov'd and convey'd, are, like the Spring and Wheels, ſecret, and not diſcern'd by any, but thoſe that know the Machin. And yet there are, and always have been, a ſort of Men, who have neither Opportunities nor Faculties to dive into the Myſteries of State, to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Adminiſtration of Public Affairs; who notwithſtanding are always Cenſuring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60506:13"/>and Accuſing the Government; always crying out, <hi>There is Corruption Above, and Things are not well carry'd.</hi> Theſe Men are fit Tools in the hands of Ambitious and Politic Men, and may be turn'd to what purpoſes they pleaſe. They are eaſily perſwaded to believe their own Cenſures; firſt themſelves think hardly of the Government, and then will eaſily ſwallow the worſt Repreſentation Ill men can make of it. This is a Temper therefore juſt ripe for <hi>Sedition;</hi> for 'tis Natural for men to endeavour an Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or Reformation of what they think they are capable to mend. It is therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the quiet living under any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that this Cenſorious Humor be kept down: For <hi>Rebellion</hi> hath its degrees, firſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Government, then believe our own Cenſures, then hate it, then endeavour to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it. Deſtroy therefore this Monſter in the <hi>Embrio,</hi> kill Rebellion in the Seed: Let us do (what is very reaſonable), never undertake to cenſure what we do not comprehend; Let us believe well of the Government, 'till we have plain Reaſon to do otherwiſe; Let us make but the ſame allowances to the Actions of Princes in their Adminiſtrations, as we would have to our own in our ſmall Affairs, and then what Spots and Blemiſhes ſoever foul and malicious Eyes may ſpye, the Government (in its whole
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60506:13"/>frame and management) will appear to us beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and admirable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Which is neer of Kin to the former, <hi>Have a care of entertaining unreaſonable Fears and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies.</hi> Theſe have been the Incendiaries which for many years have inflam'd the Nation; and theſe are the Tools Deſigning Men have wrought with, to unſettle mens Minds and make them Mutinous. It is ſomewhat ſtrange, that the ſame methods of Deceit ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſo long, that a Nation ſhould be near twice Ruining in the memory of Man by the ſame Stratagems. <hi>Jealouſies</hi> and <hi>Fears</hi> were the Cry of the late ſad Times; and have we not yet ſuffer'd enough by ſuch Inſinuations? ſhall we again be tempted to ſwallow that Bait, which already (in our memory) hath ſpilt ſo ſo much Blood, and made ſuch havock of <hi>Engliſh</hi> men? Let us but reflect upon the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies it acted, what Miſeries have thereby been brought upon a Diſtracted People, and it will certainly make us wary, how we again are led away by ſuch Devices. When ſuch things are offer'd and obtruded, 'twould make any Conſidering man ſuſpect ſome lurking Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; that thoſe Men had ſome Deſign upon the Government, who would endeavour ſo fouly to repreſent it. If therefore we would have our <hi>Fears</hi> work rightly, let us be afraid of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60506:14"/>ſuch Temptations. The Miſchiefs and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of a Rebellious War have ſufficiently evidenc'd, that we have fear'd where no Fear was, that the means we took to releaſe our Fears, brought us truly under thoſe Miſchiefs we were before only jealous of. And what are we now afraid of? Do we fear the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the Government, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the eſtabliſh'd Laws? And is <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> a Remedy? Will being Tumultuary under the Government releaſe us? This is but to do the Thing we fear, to create Real Evils for fear of Imaginary ones, actually to deſtroy the Government and the Laws, for fear only leſt they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd. Our Fears therefore are on the wrong ſide; and we ought as much (at leaſt) to fear, leſt by any <hi>Seditious</hi> and <hi>Mutinous Practices</hi> Deſolation be brought upon the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Our Fears of Injury to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Laws, ſhould work in us to be Peaceable under both; for if we are really afraid of any ſuch Inconveniences, 'tis ſure but reaſonable for us, not to contribute any thing thereto by our own Behavioun, otherwiſe it will be thought, that we do not purely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Ruine of the Laws and Government, only we take it Ill, that any Body elſe ſhould Ruine them beſide our Selves.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60506:14"/>3. <hi>Beware of Imprudent and Intemperate Zeal.</hi> This is a Weed of Religion that ſpoils the whole Crop: A Tare that not only corrupts, but blaſts the whole Field. For Religion is, of it ſelf, the moſt calm and quiet thing in the whole World; but when 'tis heated by <hi>Diſorderly Zeal,</hi> 'tis the moſt Tempeſtuous. Men who meaſure the ſtrength of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, only by the warmth they have for ſome Opinions, are the ſooneſt fired of any People, and will break through all Bounds to proſecute the things they are Zealous for. If therefore the Government oppoſes or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenances thoſe Opinions, the hot Zealot is uneaſie and fretting, the Laws cannot hold him, and he is ready (upon every turn) to attempt ſomething for the Security of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The Cauſe he undertakes for, he thinks is good; and this will ſanctifie the uſe of Means, which otherwiſe upon other accounts would not be ſo warrantable. The Killing a man, not Judicially Condemn'd, is Murder; but when <hi>Phineahs</hi> without Trial and Form of Law, out of Zeal to God's Glory kill'd <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi> it was his Righteouſneſs and his Crown: ſo as thoſe Ways which are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Illegal, yet if they be for Defence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and for Prevention of Idolatry, they are not only juſtifiable, but Heroically good.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60506:15"/>Not now to conſider that Caſe of <hi>Phineahs</hi> and the ſtate of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Zealots, who acted by peculiar and appropriate meaſures, by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Commiſſion, when they were under the immediate Government of GOD, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now be pretended: We ſhall find beſides ſufficient Reaſon to be careful of ſucking in any ſuch Principles, if we conſider, That, if this were admitted, <hi>Religion</hi> would be the greateſt Fire-brand in the World, and ſerve for little uſe elſe, but to diſturb Common-wealths, and ſet Men together by the Ears; for 'tis but for ſome Cunning men to perſwade the People, That their <hi>Religion</hi> is in danger, that <hi>Idolatry</hi> is coming in upon them, and then they may Plot and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, and Aſſociate for Inſurrections and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and do any thing; for their Cauſe is the Cauſe of God, and their Earneſtneſs in it is their Vertue and Glory. And in truth, there is ſcarcely any thing ſo bad and barbarous, which hath not already been acted under this Principle. And now is there nothing elſe in Religion, but <hi>Zeal?</hi> Are not <hi>Peace, Humility, Patience, Obedience to Government,</hi> are not theſe principal Parts of it? and muſt theſe be eaten up by that which is only an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendage, and no Duty commanded for it ſelf? Theſe are the ſubſtantial Parts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and <hi>Zeal</hi> (at the beſt) is but the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60506:15"/>Guard of it; and 'tis very unreaſonable, that what God order'd for Defence of theſe things ſhould be the greateſt means of Deſtroying them. 'Tis true indeed, every Man (in his ſtation) is oblig'd to promote God's Glory and Chriſtian Religion; but then it is by thoſe Ways only which Religion allows. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were as Zealous for <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> as any, and Advanc'd it more than ever any ſince; but the Ways they took were <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Peace, Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Suffering.</hi> Never any Tumults and Rebellions heard of, 'till <hi>Zeal</hi> became extravagant and over-grown; and not only grew too ſtrong for, but ſwallowed up all the reſt of the Vertues: And if theſe Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices were warranted by Chriſtianity, if Men might make uſe of Tumultuary and Seditious Ways, to ſecure or ſet up Religion, what a woful Condition would a Chriſtian Prince be in, whoſe Kingdom was divided into Factions, and where are ſeveral Parties of differing Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions in Religion: For all think themſelves in the Right, and all others in the Wrong, and commonly call the contrary Opinions, <hi>Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtianiſm.</hi> Now if all theſe think their Zeal for their reſpective Ways obliges them to all poſſible Means to ſet them up, and deſtroy the contrary, and if they are Luke-warm if they do not do it.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60506:16"/>If <hi>Papiſts</hi> may hire <hi>Ruffians</hi> to Piſtol the KING, if he do not ſet up <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation:</hi> If <hi>Presbyterians</hi> may fight againſt him, if he do not pull down <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and place in their ſtead <hi>Claſſis's</hi> and <hi>Lay-Elders:</hi> If <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents</hi> may cut of his Head, if he do not root out the Idolatry of the <hi>Surplice</hi> and the Dagon of the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and enact Laws for the Congregational Way: If the <hi>Quakers</hi> may deny him and teſtifie againſt him, if he do not aboliſh all other Ways, and ſet up <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> and <hi>New Lights.</hi> In this Caſe what can a King do? 'Tis impoſſible to ſet up more than One, and then all the reſt are to be Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom and Vexatious, to become his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to purſue him as an Adverſary to Truth. I ſay therefore, That if <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> did warrant ſuch things, it would be look'd upon as the <hi>Make-bate</hi> of the World; It would be eſteem'd, what its Enemies repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it, a moſt peſtilent Hereſie, and all Governours would uſe their utmoſt to Root it out of their Kingdoms, as utterly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Quiet and Peace of them. Whereas in truth there is nothing more the Intereſt of Governours, than to ſettle <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> among the People, becauſe there is nothing more governable than a good Chriſtian, nothing more Orderly and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60506:16"/>than the meaſures of Religion but then it is Religion, not acted by furious and bitter Zeal, but by its own mild and ſober Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Be not over-fond and haſty of joyning with any Diſſenting Party.</hi> Here I muſt premiſe, That I do not lay this PLOT upon any particular Party of Diſſenters, nor deſire to inſinuate, that They (as Diſſenters) are ingag'd in it. God forbid that things of this Nature ſhould be charg'd upon any but thoſe that are found Guilty: But as King <hi>JAMES,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praem. to Apol.</note> ſpeaking of the <hi>Powder Treaſon,</hi> ſays, <hi>That it was only plotted by Papiſts, and They only lead thereto by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous Zeal, for the advancement of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Upon which account the Parliament next ſitting us'd all means of Trial, to know if there were any more of that mind left in the Country. And he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apol. King</hi> James<hi>'s Works, pag.</hi> 265.</note> 
               <hi>That the Oath of Allegiance was Ordain'd for making a difference between the Civilly obedient Papiſts, and the Perverſe Diſciples of the Powder Treaſon.</hi> And thus far this is applicable, That this horrid Plot was contriv'd by Men who favour'd their Way; that there were no leſs than Three of their Teachers actually engag'd in it; that the Chief and Principal Plotters had Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of great Strength and Supply from them. Now although it is not reaſonable, that the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60506:17"/>Faults of ſome ſhould be tranſlated to a Whole Party; yet this ſhould make every Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious Man very jealous of himſelf, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully examine whether his Practices have any ſuch tendency; whether there hath been any juſt Occaſion given for Contriving men to have ſuch Expectations from them; and if there hath, then ſpeedily to alter them, and give ſuch Teſtimonies of Loyalty, as the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may not ſuſpect, nor the Sedicious hope for any ſuch thing from them. I do not deſire to reflect, nor would lay an Aſperſion, eſpecially upon a Whole-Party, for that is to Scandalize by Whole-Sale; but I hope every Good man will be careful of theſe following Doctrines, which were broach'd by thoſe who Diſſent from the <hi>Church of England:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Princes for juſt Cauſes may be Depos'd.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Knox. <hi>Hiſt.</hi> pag. 372.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Princes be Tyrants againſt God and his Truth,
<note place="margin">Id. Ep. <hi>to</hi> Engl. <hi>and</hi> Scot. fo. 77.</note> their Subjects are freed from their Oaths of Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is in the Power of the People to give the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion to whom they will.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Buchanan. <hi>de Jure Regni,</hi> p. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It were well if Rewards were appointed by the People for ſuch as ſhould kill Tyrants,
<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 40.</note> as commonly there is for thoſe who kill Wolves or Bears, or catch their Whelps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The People may Arraign their Prince.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 62.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Miniſters may Excommunicate him;
<note place="margin">Pag. 70.</note> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60506:17"/>he that by Excommunication is caſt into Hell, is not worthy to enjoy any Life upon Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is lawful to Kill wicked Kings and Tyrants.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Goodman</hi> p. 99. 103. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
                  </note> The Subjects did kill the Queens Highneſs</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaliah; Jehu <hi>kill'd the Queens Majeſty,</hi> Jezabel; Elias <hi>(being no Magiſtrate) kill'd the Queens Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Chaplains,</hi> Baal<hi>'s Prieſts. Theſe Examples are left for our Inſtruction; where this Juſtice is not executed, the State is moſt Corrupt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When Magiſtrates do ceaſe to do their Duties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. 180, 184, 210. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
               </note> (i. e. <hi>in Depoſing and Killing Kings) the People are as it were without Officers, and then God giveth the Sword into their hands, and he himſelf is become immediately their Head; for to the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude a portion of the Sword of Juſtice is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, from the which no Perſon, King, Queen, or Emperour (being an Idolater) is exempt; He muſt dye the Death. The People</hi> (Numb. 25.) <hi>did hang up certain of their Heads and Captains, Which ought to be for a perpetual Example of their Duty in the like defection from God, to hang up ſuch Rulers as ſhall draw them from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If neither the Inferiour Magiſtrates, nor the greateſt part of the People will do their Duties, then the Miniſter muſt Excommunicate ſuch a King; any Miniſter may do it againſt the Greateſt Prince. God will ſend the reſt of the People (which are willing to do their Duty, but not able) ſome</hi> Moſes <hi>or</hi> Othoniel.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60506:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If they know any</hi> Jonathan, <hi>they muſt go to him to be their Captain; and he ought not to refuſe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Magiſtrates without fear tranſgreſs Gods Law,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Goodman,</hi> pag. 139.</note> and command others to do the ſame, they have loſt that Honour and Obedience, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their Subjects ow'd them; and ought no more to be taken for Magiſtrates, but to be examin'd, accus'd, condemn'd and puniſh'd, as private Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Word of God (when others will not do it) a Private man having ſome ſpecial inward Call,
<note place="margin">Obed. p. 110. <hi>Quoted by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> Bancroft <hi>in Dangerous Poſitiens.</hi>
                  </note> may kill a Tyrant, as</hi> Moſes <hi>did the</hi> Egyptian, <hi>as</hi> Phineahs <hi>the Leacherous, as</hi> Ahud <hi>did King</hi> Eglon: <hi>or otherwiſe a Private man may do ſo, if he be commanded, or permitted by the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps by this time you may think I am quoting the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and picking <hi>King-killing</hi> Principles out of their Books; and indeed the Doctrines are ſo very like, they cannot eaſily be diſtinguiſhed. But theſe are the Poſitions of <hi>Knox, Buchanan, Goodman,</hi> Famous Leaders and Setters up of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline: and a man would imagine the preſent Plot was fetch'd from theſe Authors, the Doctrine and the Practice do ſo exactly agree; and many Doctrines of the ſame Nature were publiſh'd and practis'd in the late Times. It
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60506:18"/>is to be hoped, that many of our preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters do not ariſe to the height of theſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions; however this Doctrine and this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour too coming from men of their Way, would make every good Man very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider before he aſſembles with them. And in truth All Diſſenters of every kind (as might eaſily be made appear) when they come to ſtate the meaſures of Obedience, are very looſe and ſlippery, very Injurious to Princes, and ſuch as diminiſh the Rights of Government: And therefore,</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Be Conſtant and Devout in the Communion of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as it is eſtabliſh'd by Law.</hi> It is the peculiar glory of this Church, that it never hath either by Doctrine or Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, in the leaſt encourag'd or countenanc'd any thing tending to <hi>Treaſon, Sedition</hi> or <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</hi> Men of this Communion have been eminent Sufferers for, but never Oppoſers of Lawful Authority. Here Obedience to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is taught by the ſame Meaſures it was by our Saviour, by his Apoſtles, and by the Primitive Chriſtians. And this is ſo very obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that the worſt of her Enemies, who have loaded her with other Contumelies, could never yet have the face to charge her with <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Reſiſtance of Authority.</hi> Here therefore let us faſten our ſelves, and we are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60506:19"/>ſecure from all Temptations of this kind; and it is impoſſible that any Man, ſo long as he continues in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be a Mutineer or a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Let us conſult both the former, and the modern Arts of Diſturbance, and we ſhall find that Ambitious men never thought to make a Game here; they always look'd upon it as a fruitleſs Attempt to practiſe upon Men of theſe Principles, but the ways have been firſt to divide the Church, to withdraw Men from her Communion, and then they hop'd (in time) to work them to their Purpoſes, and to bring them to make Head againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Were Men but united in this Communion, there would be no room left for <hi>Rebellion,</hi> no Inſtruments for Deſigning Men to work upon; All the Pleas of fighting for Religion, of reſiſting the Magiſtrate under the cover of <hi>Conſcience</hi> would ſoon be at an end. Let us all therefore heartily embrace this; Let us be uniform to the Tenents and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, as well as to the external Adminiſtration of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Let us as well be the Sons of it in mind, as in outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity: And there cannot (in humane mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures) be a better Expedient to preſerve us from all Turbulent and Seditious Enticements.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60506:19"/>6. <hi>Let us be ſincere in the performance of the purpoſes of this Day.</hi> Let us heartily give Thanks to Almighty GOD for this Deliverance of our Gracious Soveraign, His Royal Brother, His Loyal Subjects and His Kingdoms, from the horrid Attempts and Conſpiracies of Wicked Men: And this, (if we do it Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly) will certainly reſcue us from all kind of Diſloyal Thoughts. He that (as he ſhould) thanks God for the KING's Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, cannot himſelf adminiſter to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, except he prays like a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> with a devouring mind. What greater Hypocriſie, than to pour out our Thankſgiving to God for diſcovering the Contrivances againſt the Government, and at the ſame time to have mutinous and ungovernable Inclinations? This is to mock God, and we pray for one thing and wiſh for another. Let our Minds therefore go with our Prayers, and if it doth not find us, it will make us Faithful to the Government; for Prayer is of a transforming nature, and if we are juſt to God and our ſelves in it, it will make us of the ſame Nature and Complexion, our Prayers will ſlide into our Practices, and we ſhall live as we pray. Let us all therefore (as we have the greateſt Reaſon) from the bottom of our Hearts, return our Thankfulleſt Acknowledgments to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60506:20"/>Almighty GOD for his Infinite Goodneſs, that, by his good Providence, hath kept our KING, His Royal Brother, and our Nation, from becoming a Prey to Bloody and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Men. Let us do this in the ſincerity of our Souls, and then as for the preſent it winds up our Thoughts in contemplation of the Divine Mercy; ſo it will for the future influence our Lives. As it now frames us to be Thankful to GOD; ſo (if we are not Hypocrites) it will make us Loyal to the KING.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60506:20"/>
            <head>SERMONS lately printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. A <hi>Diſcourſe to prove the ſtrongeſt Temptations conquerable by</hi> Chriſtians; <hi>in a Sermon preached before the</hi> Lord Mayor, <hi>Jan.</hi> 14. 1676/7.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>The</hi> Spirit of Enthuſiaſm, <hi>exorcis'd in a Sermon preached before the</hi> Univerſity of Oxford, <hi>on</hi> Act Saturday, <hi>July</hi> 11. 1680.</item>
               <item>3. Peculium Dei: <hi>A Diſcourſe about the</hi> Jews, <hi>as the</hi> Peculiar People of God; <hi>in a Sermon preached before the</hi> Aldermen <hi>and</hi> Citizens <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>Febr.</hi> 6. 1680/1.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>The</hi> True Notion of Perſecution, <hi>ſtated in a Sermon preached at the Time of the late Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution for the</hi> French Proteſtants.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>A Sermon preached before the</hi> Lord Mayor <hi>at</hi> Bow Church, <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1681/2.</item>
               <item>6. The Moral Shechinah; <hi>Or a Diſcourſe of Gods Glory; in a Sermon preached at the laſt</hi> York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire Feaſt, <hi>June</hi> 11. 1682.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All Six by <hi>George Hicks,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Proſecution no Perſecution; <hi>Or the Difference between Suffering for</hi> Diſobedience <hi>and</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>in a Sermon preached at</hi> Bury St. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munds, Suffolk, <hi>March</hi> 22. 1681.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:60506:21"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Modern</hi> Phariſees, <hi>ſhewing the Principles of the preſent</hi> Jeſuits <hi>and</hi> Puritans, <hi>to be of the ſame evil Influence with the Ancient</hi> Phariſees. <hi>Both by</hi> Nath. Bisbie, <hi>D.D.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Calamy<hi>'s Sermon preached before the</hi> L. Mayor <hi>at</hi> Bow-Church, <hi>May</hi> 29. 1682.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Kidder<hi>'s Sermon, preached before the</hi> Lord Mayor, <hi>July</hi> 16. 1682.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Fowler<hi>'s Sermon, preached at the</hi> Aſſizes <hi>at</hi> Glouceſter, <hi>Aug.</hi> 7. 1681.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Young<hi>'s Sermon, preached before the</hi> Lord Mayor, <hi>Febr.</hi> 4. 1682.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Hopkin<hi>'s Sermon, preached before the</hi> Lord Mayor, <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1683.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Foxe<hi>'s Sermon, preached at the</hi> Herefordſhire-Feaſt, <hi>July</hi> 3. 1683.</item>
               <item>The Originals of Rebellion; <hi>Or,</hi> The end of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration; <hi>in a Sermon preached</hi> Jan. 30. 1682.</item>
               <item>The Rebellious City Deſtroyed; <hi>being an Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary Sermon in memory of the Dreadful Fire of</hi> London, <hi>Sept.</hi> 2. 1666. <hi>Preached</hi> 1682.</item>
               <item>Loyalty Proteſting againſt Popery, <hi>and</hi> Phanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm Popiſhly Affected, <hi>in a Sermon preached</hi> Nov. 5. 1682. <hi>both by</hi> William Wray, <hi>M. A.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ahitophel</hi>'s Policy Defeated; <hi>in a Sermon preached on the Thanksgiving-Day,</hi> Sept. 9. 1683.</item>
               <item>Samaritaniſm Reviv'd; <hi>in a Sermon preached by</hi> Luke Milbourne <hi>on the late Thanksgiving-Day,</hi> Sept. 9. 1683.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60506:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
